Finding Aid for a Collection of Ethiopic Manuscripts LSC.0937
UCLA Library Special Collections
A collection of Ethiopic manuscripts
various dates
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.0937
1 unknown (13 boxes)
Collection contains 64 Ethiopian manuscripts.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
PORTIONS OF THIS COLLECTION HAVE BEEN DIGITIZED. See the Existence and Location of Copies note for the link to the digitized materials.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
999643443606533
Scope and Content
Collection contains 64 Ethiopian manuscripts. Of these, 14 are magical prayers, 10 of which are in scrolls. Most of the manuscripts are service books of Ethiopian Orthodox Church. There is one manuscript which is the prayer book of Beta Israel (Ethiopian Jewish community); it is one of very few Jewish manuscripts written in Ethiopic (Ge'ez) and Agaw. Most of the manuscripts are written in the Ethiopic (Ge'ez) language but there are some manuscripts in Amharica.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digitized materials are available electronically at https://digital.library.ucla.edu/catalog/x3xg9000zz-89112.
Ge'ez descriptions available
To obtain a copy of this finding aid which contains Ethiopic language (Ge'ez) descriptions of the material, please contact UCLA Library Special Collections. A computer with the Ge'ez font installed is necessary to view the Ge'ez descriptions.
Ethiopic manuscripts.
- Title (Romanized): Qeddasé Maryam, Malek'a Kidana Mehrat Uniform title: Anaphora of Mary, Images of the Saints Title (English): The Anaphora of Mary and Image of Kidana Meherat (Covenant of Mary)., 1842-1854.; Manuscript number: 1; Layout: two columns of text, 14 lines of text per page Size: 97 mm x 64 mm x 28 mm (heighth, width, spine) Velum, 120 pages (60 leaves) the manuscript composed in six quires 10 leaves each Text in black ink. Beginning of each prayer, instructions for the priests and deacons, Saint Mary's name and the name of the Holy Trinity are in red ink Binding: stamped leather over wooden boards. Written by a single hand. No drawings. Quires?? (Box 1)
  Biography
  Based on the size of the manuscript (it is too small for church service), we can say the purpose of this manuscript is for private use.
  Provenance
  On p. 82, the previous owner's name is overwritten with ink and, at the bottom of the page, it says "Ayela Eyasus's origin is in Wallaga."
  Scope and Content
  One of the the official fourteen anaphoras of the Ethiopian orthdox church. Praise for St. Mary and discourse on the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit as the major part of the liturgy.
- Title (Romanized): Arede'et, Sena Feterat, Mes?ira Hayamnot, Amestu A'emada Mes?ir Uniform title: The Book of Disciples, Beauty of the Creation, Mystery of the Faith Title (English): The Book of Disciples, Beauty of the Creation, Mystery of the Faith (The Five Pillars of Mystery)., 18th-19th c.; Manuscript number: 2; Layout: one column of text, the first book 14 lines of text per page the second book with different hand has different lines per page. 140mm x 95m x 73m Vellum, 300 pages Text in black ink. Beginning of each prayer and the names of Jesus, Christ, Mary, and also the name of the owner are in red ink Binding: Wooden board. The second part of Beauty of the Creation is written by another scribe in poor handwriting. Quires? (Box 1)
  The manuscript contains four books. Book of the Disciple is the Christian version of the same book which is also used by the Beta Israel (Falasha or Ethiopian Jew). It narrates how Jesus told his disciples his hidden names. The second book, The Beauty of the Creation, also lists what God created in six days. The Five Pillars of Mystery teaches the basic doctrine of the Ethiopian Church in catechism format.
  The owner (scribe?) was Gabra Heyewat. On pp.89, 90, 97, 99, 100, 120, his name is erased and over it inserted the second owner's name Waleda Hawareyat. The scribe of Beauty of the Creation mentions Abuna Wold (pp. 180).
- Title (Romanized): Weddasé Maryam, Anqa?a Berhan, Yewédeswa Mala'ekt, Malk'a Maryam, Malek'a Eyasus Uniform title: Wedase Mareyam Title (English): Praise of Mary, The Gate of the Light, Angeles Praise Her, The Image of Mary, and the Image of Jesus., late 19th c.; Manuscript number: 3; Layout: Two columns on vellum, 17 lines per page Vellum, 128 pages Size: 147 mm x 105 mm x 30 mm Binding: stamped red leather over the board Text in black ink, Jesus and Mary's name and the beginning of each prayer (maleke) are in red. The manuscript is composed of quires of ten leaves each. Some illustrations. (Box 1)
  On p.126, the owner wrote in Amharic and Ge'ez that "this book belongs to Gabera Hana."
- Title (Romanized): ?oma Deggwa Uniform title: Church Hymns Title (English): Hymns for Lent., Late 19th-early 20th cent.; Manuscript number: 4; Vellum, 222 pages. Two columns per page, 21 lines of text per page. Size: 161 mm x 124 mm x 50 mm Text mainly in black ink. The musical tones, the type of song, and the day for that song are in red ink. Small hand. Some missing musical notes added in blue ink (pen) Musical notations throughout, above each line of the hymn. Binding: wooden board with leather spine, in sewn plastic case with applique and cloth strap. String The manuscript is composed of quires of ten leaves each. Illustration of Saint Yared p. 4. (Box 1)
  Soma Degguwa is one of St. Yared's well-known hymn books. It is the standard for traditional church education. Learning Soma Degguwa is the second great step after finishing reciting psalm.
  The owner is listed in pencil as Tafasa of Dabera Amin Takla Haymanot (p. 1)
  Hymns for Lent season. St.Yared, the author of these hymns, divided the Lent season into eight weeks. Almost all of the hymns are constructed around the teaching and miracles of Jesus. The hymns discuss the teaching of Jesus in the Synagogue, his cleaning of the temple, the miracle of healing paralysis, the parable of the faithful servant, his discussion with Nicodimus, his teaching about his second coming, his glorious entrance into Jerusalem, his last days in Jerusalem, and his crucifixion.
- Title (Romanized): Yetbarak Egzi'abehér amelaka Esra'él … Uniform title: Prayers of the Beta Israel Title (English): Blessed Be the Lord God of Israel …., 20th.c.; Manuscript number: 5; Vellum, 200 pages Two columns, 14 lines of text per page Size: 145mm x 130mm x 40mm Text in black ink. The beginning of each section ('me'eraf), the names of God, and the angles are in red ink. Binding: without cover boards. The manuscript composed in 12 quires (Box 1)
  A rare and important collection of Beta Israel prayers in the Ge'ez and Agaw languages. Most of the Ge'ez prayers are derived from the Bible, especially from Psalms, those in Agaw are more indigenous and difficult to translate. One of the last Beta Israel books to be written in Ge'ez or Agaw. See David Appleyard, Title??? (publisher, date).
  p. 145, the owner of the book is named Abba Barok. Purchased by Prof. Wolf Leslau.
- Title (Romanized): Ma?ehafa ?emeqat Uniform title: Book of Baptism Title (English):Book of Baptism., 20th c.; Manuscript number: 6; Vellum, 72 pages One column of text, 14 lines of text per page Size: 148 mm x 110 mm x 40 mm Binding: wooden boards with leather spine Text in black ink, some names and the beginning of the prayers and instructions for Deacons and Priests are in red. The manuscript is composed of quires of eight leaves each. No illustrations. (Box 2)
  "This book belongs to Wayzaro Walatta Kidan. She gave the book to the church of Kidane Merhat" (p. 64)
- Title (Romanized): Mazemura Dawit, ?alota Nabiyat, Wedasé Maryam, Anqa?a Berhan Uniform title: Dawit Title (English): Psalter, Canticles of Old and New Testament Prophets, Praise of St. Mary, The Gate of Light., 19th c.; Manuscript number: 7; Layout: One column of text, 22 lines of text per page Vellum, 142 pages Size: 170 mm x 115 mm x 30 mm Binding: wooden boards. The front wooden board and two thirds of the Psalms pages are missing. The Psalms begin with Psalm 111 (112): 3b. The manuscript is damaged, probably by water. The text in red ink is totally washed out or faded. The manuscript composed in seven quires of two quires has 12 leaves each, four quires of 10 leaves each and one quire of 8 leaves. The text is in black ink; the name of God, angels, and saints, including the scribes and the owners, and the first line of each book, is in red ink. No illustrations. (Box 2)
- Title (Romanized): ?alot ba?eneta ?emama Ayena ?ela wa- Ayena Wareq, Mahléta ?egé, Seyefa Selassé,Qeddasé Maryam Uniform title: Prayer, Qedasé Title (English): Prayer against the Disease of Ayena ?ela and wa- Ayena Warek, Canticles of the Flower (Mary), Sword of Trinity, Anaphora of St. Mary., 20th c.; Manuscript number: 8; Layout: pp1-65 and 207-217 One column of texts. Pp75-206 and 219 two column of text Vellum, 272 pages. The first four blank pages with out page numbers. Size: 120mm x 94 mm x 40 mm Binding: stamped red leather over the board each book written with different hand. The first book of the manuscript composed in one quire of two leaves, three quires of ten leaves each and one quire of six leaves. The second book of the manuscript composed in one quire of four leave one ten leave six quires of eight leaves each one qiere of five leaves. The third book in composed in one quire of six pages. The fourth book composed one quire of ten leaves one quire of eight leaves and one quire of six leaves. Text is in black ink. Divine and saints name in red ink (Box 2)
  The magical prayer agianst ayena tela was owned by Fekada Egezi'e (pp. 2, 6, 12, 13, etc). Canticles of the Flower was owned by Hayela Sellase (pp. 141). And the second owner of that book is Waleda Mareyam (pp. 141). Sword of Trinity owned by Walda Zena Markos (pp. 209, 212, 217). The Anaphora of St. mary was owned by Walda Tensae (pp. 219, 265).
  The prayer against the disease of ayena tela uses magical names for protection from evil spirits. Mahaléta ?egé are songs for St. Mary sung during Zamana Sege (the season of flowers), the season between Meskaram (September/October) 26 and Hedar (November) 6. The seaons is the commemoration of the flight of the Holy Family to Egypt. Sword of Trinity. Praise for the Holy Trinity and prayer for protection from evil spirits and evil people.
- Title (Romanized): Ta'amera Mareyam Maqdem Tergwame Uniform title: Te'amera Mareyam Title (English): Commentary on the Introductory Rite of Almuqqa of the Miracle of Mary., 20th c.; Manuscript number: 9; Layout: One column per page, 11 lines of text per page Vellum, 134 pages. The first four pages are blank and with out page nambers Size: 100mm x 70mm x 35mm Composed of quires of eight and ten leaves each. Text in black ink. Beginning of each chapter (parts) and also the divine and church father names in red ink. Binding: wooden boards (Box 2)
  According to the tradition of the Ethiopian Orthodox Church, the introduction of the Miracles of St. Mary must be read before any other reading from the book. There are two types of introduction. The longer one presented in this manuscript is read every Sunday and on the feast of St. Mary. The introduction of the Miracles of St. Mary is also known as the Book of Order, which discusses how the book of the Miracles of St. Mary came to Ethiopia. In addition to its introduction about the honor of St. Mary and her miracles and the importance of reading her miracles, the book also lists the 33 feasts of St. Mary. Based upon the method of andmeta commentary, the author tries to comment on the introduction and points out the importance of honoring her feast and hearing the reading of the miracle. The author also explains the severity of the anathema of the fathers on those who have not followed this order.
  On p.133, Debetara Zena is mentioned as the owner.
  Commentary on the introduction to the Miracles of St. Mary; it is a rare individual commentary. The writer follows the 'anedemta' commentary style. The main theme is about the usefulness of listening to the reading of the book of the Miracles of St. Mary and keeping the 23 feasts of St. Mary
- Title (Romanized): ?abiba ?abiban; Arde?et Uniform title: Hymn to God; Book of the Disciples Title (English): The Wisest of the Wise; Book of the Disciples., Late 19th c.; Manuscript number: 10; Layout: One column of text per page,11 lines of text per page Vellum, 166 pages Size: 102 mm x 74 mm x 33 mm Binding: stamped red leather over the board The manuscript is composed of quires of eight leaves each Text is in black ink. The beginning of each chapter (parts) and prayers with divine names are in red ink. No illustrations (Box 2)
  Tebiba Tabiban is a hymn for God written in metrical poetry. For Ared'et, see MS no. …
- Title (Romanized): Deresana Mika'él Uniform title: Deresan Title (English):Homilies on St. Michael the Archangel., 19th c.; Manuscript number: 11; Vellum, 274 pages Two columns per page, 19 lines of text per page Size: 195 mm x 140 mm x 59 mm The manuscript composed of fourteen quires of two quires of four leaves, four quires of twelve leaves and eight quires of ten leaves each. Text in black ink. The beginning of each homily and the names of Jesus and the archangel Michael are in red ink. Binding: wooden board with string binding Some illustrations. (Box 2)
  These thirteen homilies are written to be read during the feasts of St. Michael each month. Each homily includes a miracle of the Archangel Michael and hymns for him.
  The original owner is unknown. The later owner inserted his name in pencil as Takela Maryam.
  A collection of thirteen homilies in honor of the Archangel Michael. Following each homily there is one miracle of St. Michael and the Synaxarium about St. Michael for each month.
- Title (Romanized): Sayefa Sellasé, Dersana Mika?él, Amestu A'emada Mes?ir Uniform title: The Sword of the Trinity, Homily of St. Michael, The Five Pillars of the Faith Title (English): The Sword of the Trinity; Homily On St. Michael; Introduction of The Five Pillars of the Faith., Late 18th.c.; Manuscript number: 12; Layout: Two columns per page,17 lines of text per page Vellum, 100 pages Size: 165 mm x 130 mm x 30 mm The manuscript is composed of quires of eight leaves each. Text is in black ink, the beginning of each prayer and divine names are in red ink. Binding: wooden board without a cover for the spine Some borders as illustrations. (Box 2)
  The previous scribe or owner's name, Takla Haymanot, has frequently been erased from the text and replaced with the name Gabera Heyewot
  Prayer to the Holy Trinity (Father, Son, and the Holy Spirit). Praise of the Trinity based on God's attributes. Theology of the Triune God. Prayer for protection from evil spirits, evil persons, magicians, and sorcerers.
- Title (Romanized): Nages (Egzi?abehér Nagesa) Uniform title: Hymns for Saints' Feasts Title (English): Enthroned (God Is Enthroned)., 20th c.; Manuscript number: 13; Layout: one column per page, thirteen lines of text per page Vellum, 222 pages Size: 135 mm x 87 mm x 48 mm Text in black ink, beginning of each nagese divine and saints' names in red ink. Binding: wooden boards. With protective vellum cover over the vellum only. Leather spine cover. The manuscript is composed of very different quires (in number of leaves and size). No illustrations. (Box 3)
  The first owner is listed as "Gabera Egezi'abeher Saneduna Qale" on p.217, the second owner is listed as "This book belongs to Dabetera Nadew's. End of Nages [the book]." (p. 2)
  Nages for feast days
- Title (Romanized): Amesetu A?emada Mes?ir; Bahera ?asab; Nags Uniform title: The Five Pillars of Mystery; Computus; Hymns Title (English): The Five Pillars of Mystery, Computus of Ethiopian Calendar; Hymns to God and Saints., Late 19th c.; Manuscript number: 14; Vellum, 120 pages; Layout: One column per page, fourteen lines of text per page Binding: wooden boards Size: 122 mm x 85 mm x 29 mm Most of the manuscript is composed of quires of eight leaves each. The text is in black ink; the name of God, angels, and saints, including the scribes and the owners, and the first line of each book, is in red ink. No illustrations. (Box 3)
  "This picture is for Aleka Hiruy" p. 1 (later addition?)
- Title (Romanized): Mesalyata Salomon; Daqiqa Nabiyat Uniform title: Book of Proverbs and Minor Prophets Title (English): Proverbs of Solomon; The Minor Prophets., 19th-20th c,.; Manuscript number: 15; Vellum, 178 pages Binding: wooden boards Size: 185mm x 165mm x 65mm Text is in black ink, some names and titles of the chapters are in red. The manuscript is composed of ten quires of one quire of four leave one quire of eight leaves eight quires of ten leaves each. (Box 3)
  Amesetu Masahefeta Salomon (the five books of Solomon) is the name which is given to Proverbs, Tagsas, Wisdom, and Ecclesiastes and Song of Songs.In this manuscript Song of Song is not included. The reason seems to be that Song of Songs is usually attached with Psalms and it becomes part of the church service book. The manuscript also contains the books of the 12 minor prophets. Like the other Christian traditions, the Ethiopian scholars also divided the book of the prophets of the Old Testament into two parts, Abayet Nabiyat (major prophets) and Daqiqa Nabiyat (minor prophets). Critical editions and translations of parts of the Ethiopic versions of the books of Solomon and minor prophets of Ethiopic version were conducted, especially in Europe. For full discussion see ??????.
  There is a note in Amharic from Abba Matthias, the Catholic Bishop of Shoa: "this book is for Tasaruye Waleda Selasse. I, Abba Matthias, put the seal twice by mistake." p.177 Tasefa Iyasus is also mentioned as the owner.
  Part of the wisdom and prophetic books of the bible, which include Proverbs, Ecclesiastes, the Wisdom of Solomon, and the books of the minor prophets
- Title (Romanized): Saatat; Nages; Liton Uniform title: The Hours; Hymns for Saints; Liton Title (English):The Hours; Hymns for Saints; Liton., early 18th c.; Manuscript number: 16; Layout: Two columns per page,13 lines of text per page Vellum, 226 pages Size: 145 mm x 140 mm x 68 mm Binding: wooden boards Text is in black ink; the beginning of some prayers and St. Mary's name are in red ink. The manuscript is composed of fifteen quires of eight and ten leaves each. Some leaves missing at the end. (Box 3)
  On p. 2 appears the names of Priest Wolda Abb and Priest Habta Giyoregis. Someone has inserted as a bookmark a blank form of colonial Italy's 'Telegramma in partaenza'. On the back of the form, it is written in Amharic, 'I, Mekonnen Gezaw, borrowed from my father Abba Jerom four Ethiopian Birr. Regarding my borrowing, I have confirmed it with my signature. I swear by the name of my father Abba Jerome. The guarantor is Aleqa Like Tebebt. Genebot (May ) 16, 1938 [EC]."
- Title (Romanized): Sayefa Malakot Uniform title: The Sword of Divinity Title (English): The Sword of Divinity., 20th c.; Manuscript number: 17; Layout: One column per page, eight lines of text per page Vellum, 36 pages Size: 120 mm x 85 mm 12 mm Text in red ink. Some faded parts are written for the second time in blue ink. Last page in blue ink. Binding: Cardboard boards and string. Illustrations. Quires? (Box 3)
  Magical names with magical illustrations. It is a prayer asking God for protection from various demonic and personal attacks.
- Title (Romanized): Dersana Mika?él Uniform title: Deresan Title (English):Homily on St. Michael the Archangel., 20th c.; Manuscript number: 18; Layout: one column per page; 19 lines of text per page Vellum, 244 pages Size: 214 mm x 149 mm x 60 mm Binding: smooth wooden boards with leather case and strap Text in black ink, the archangels and saints' names and titles of the chapters are in red. The manuscript is composed of quires of four, ten, twelve, and sixteen leaves each Illustrations: some drawings and illustrated borders at the beginning of each month. Pp.2, 3, 234, 238, 242 Illustrations of Mary, St. Michael, and St. Gabriel with pen and color. Pp. 25, 42, 79, 154, 244 Crude drawings with pencil. (Box 4)
  Thirteen homilies attributed to Ethiopian and other church fathers.
  On p.78, the first owner is listed as Wolda Mareyam. The second or last owner wrote his name and his family's name in many place in the text: Gabra Selase, Senesata Mareyam (Tajitu), Gabera Madehen, Gabera Selase (Bafeqadu).
  Collection of thirteen homilies in honor of the Archangel Michael. Following each homily there is related one miracle of St. Michael and the synaxarium about St. Michael for the twelfth day of each month.
- Title (Romanized): Ta?amera Maryam; Ta?amera Eyasus; Ta?amera Giyorgis; Ta?amera Mikaél;Ta?amera Gaber?él Uniform title: Taamer Title (English): The Miracles of Mary, Miracle of Jesus, Miracle of St. George, Miracle of Michael, Miracle of Gabriel., 20th.; Manuscript number: 19; Vellum, 170 Pages. Two columns per page, 19 lines of text per page. Size: 210 mm x 160 mm x 52 mm Binding is wooden boards with stamped leather and string to tie closed. The majority of the manuscript is composed of quires of ten leaves each. The text is in black ink; the divine names of the saints and also the first few words of the miracles with the Trinitarian formula are in red ink. No illustrations (Box 4)
  The collection of miracles included in this manuscript are part of the readings for morning prayers. Local saints or patron saints or angels of that particular church can be added in the readings of collected miracles. But these miracles are the most popular among laity and clergy. The collection of the Miracles of Mary are always at the center of the readings. The Miracles of St. Mary have a special introduction.
  The owners were Gabera Madehen and Gabera Hiwot (passim).
  Collection of the Miracles of Jesus, St. Mary, St. George, St. Michael, and St. Gabriel.
- Title (Romanized): Lefafa Sedeq; Manegada Samay Uniform title: Magical Prayers Title (English):The Bandlet of Righteousness, The Way of Heaven., 20th c.; Manuscript number: 20; Vellum, folded a concertina Size: 48 mm x 55 mm x 15 mm Binding: Faced with paper board and tied with string. On two strips of vellum. The text is in black ink; the divine names, the saints, and the name of the owner with the Trinitarian formula are in red ink. Two illustrations in crude hand. (Box 4)
  The Bandlet of Righteousness is a magical book which is very popular among the laity and nuns of the Ethiopian Orthodox church. In the past, like the Egyptian book of the dead, it was buried with the dead, but this tradition is no longer common.
  The owner is Le'ula Qal Yeheyes and his Christan name is Gabera Mareyam.
  It is claimed that The Bandlet of Righteousness was written by the "holy hand of God the Father" and given to St. Mary before Christ was born. It contains prayers and the hidden names of God.
- Title (Romanized): Mazemura Dawit, Asmat Uniform title: Magical Prayers Title (English): Psalms (for magical purposes)., 20th.; Manuscript number: 21; Vellum, folded like concertina, text on both sides. Size: 60 mm x 65 mm x 5 mm No binding, composed of two strips of vellum. The text is in black ink, but like other magical books, the beginning of each prayer and some magical names ('asmat') and magical tables are in red ink. No illustrations. (Box 4)
  In the tradition of the Dabtara (the unordained clergy of the Ethiopian orthodox church), parts of the Psalms are useful for magical purposes. The scribe of this magical book is himself Dabtara. Added at the end of the Psalms are other magical prayers and claims that reciting these prayers can bring love and wealth.The instruction is in Amharic mixed with some Ge'ez words.